marriage is clearly an evolutionary
elaboration on something that in another
creature would we call mate guarding
mate guarding is a situation in which
one of the mates typically the male
follows the female around to ensure that
her progeny is produced by him in human
beings this has been augmented
tremendously to add all sorts of depth
and symmetry to the mate guarding and in
fact it looks much closer in many ways
to something like what we might see in
other monogamous primates in monogamous
primates individuals will sit together
and they will actually duet I believe
this is true for all monogamous primates
rather than human beings that the male
and the female will gather repeatedly
and they will sit on the same branch and
sing together so I'm not saying that
never happens in humans but it's not an
obligate behavior in humans whereas it
is an applicant behavior in TV monkeys
and Gibbons and other other monogamous
primates the important thing to realize
though is that once you have a structure
like mate guarding and then it begins to
be elaborated for other purposes that
all sorts of stuff gets built into that
relationship and so there's obviously a
very intensive kind of reciprocation
within the marital context where males
and females are contributing in many
ways equally though not the same things
to the relationship and so they're both
providing for what ultimately is the
basis for family that's that's what the
purpose of these bonds originally was
and it doesn't it's not something that
has to be maintained we could repurpose
marital relationships for for things
other than producing offspring but that
is that is ultimately why the
relationship evolved
in fact most human societies have almost
certainly not been monogamous and you
can see in the small but measurable bit
of size diverse dimorphism in human
males and human females that there has
been some history of non-monogamy that
said most people on earth today derive
from populations that are at least
nominally monogamous which begins to
tell an interesting tale the different
mating systems that we have we have
monogamy one male and one female bonded
together we have polygyny which is a
male and multiple females we have
polyandry which is one female and
multiple males and we have promiscuity
which is multiple males and multiple
females monogamy is the most common
system on earth today polygyny would be
the second most common and historically
probably the most common mild polygyny
polyandry is exceedingly rare though
there are circumstances where human
beings end up in a polyandrous situation
where a female will have multiple
husbands interestingly those cases all
seem to involve brothers marrying the
same woman which reduces the cost to
those males genetically of having
another male father children with their
wife and then there's promiscuity which
probably has been exceedingly rare in
human history but is essentially the
basis for what is now being called
polyamory and people are experimenting
with this mode whether that makes sense
is an interesting question but in a
certainly something people are
interested in at the moment
each of these mating systems are
evolutionary responses to particular
kinds of conditions there are virtually
no conditions in particular -
promiscuity makes sense and the reason
for that is that human babies are
extremely needy and because they're
extremely needy females are absolutely
required to care for them apart
see and nursing are both very labor
intensive and so females are incapable
of having a low investment relationship
with offspring and that means that they
have every reason to be exceedingly
choosy about with whom they mate and one
of the things that they are most choosy
about is evidence that a male will stick
around and invest in these very needy
offspring so promiscuity is pretty rare
for that reason polyandry is pretty rare
because males are selected to avoid
letting other males mate with their pair
bonded females because the evolutionary
costs of raising another man's offspring
is so high so doing so when the other
male is a brother reduces that cost by
50%
still we only see it in circumstances
where the habitat is so marginal that
two individuals have trouble producing
enough labor to raise children
successfully and they need a third a
third that does not increase the number
of babies produced so that would have to
be a male rather than a female monogamy
I would argue evolves when you have
nonzero some dynamics like a new
continent or something that a population
is going to spread across and producing
new individuals of the highest rate is
favored in order to capture that entire
new territory
monogamy is advantageous because it
brings every adult into child-rearing
and the limit on the number of babies
produced has a lot to do with the amount
that is being invested in taking care of
new offspring so raising them and
getting them fed and then allowing
females to move on to their next
offspring is prioritized in circumstance
where there's new territory to fill with
people and so it selects for monogamy so
I would answer I would I would argue
that the reason that human populations
have shifted in recent millenia in the
direction of monogamy has to do with the
fact that it was also an age in which
lots of land masses that were either
under-exploited or that were inhabited
by people who did not have the
technology to defend them resulted in
populations moving into those places and
spreading across them
I'm not sure that this answer actually
requires us to specify which version of
marriage we're talking about really the
point is you have a bond between two
people and the fact that one of those
people may have a bond with somebody
else doesn't say anything one way or the
other about the bond that they have so
let's talk about monogamy because it's
the simplest case but I don't think it's
a limited answer the terminology that
surrounds marriage actually gives us an
indication about what kind of
relationship this is and I'm always
shocked that we never discussed the
implications because they're right in
front of us when you marry somebody
their siblings become your siblings in
law their parents become your parents in
law you are stepping into what is
effectively a sibling relationship and
in fact marriage has a lot in common
with a regular sibling relationship
marriage is in spite of the mythology
that often surrounds them are extremely
complicated relationships and there is
tension and there's a lot of richness to
them in much the same way that there is
a sibling relationship and the reason
for that is pretty obvious which is just
like siblings spouses have real things
at stake and their interests are not a
hundred percent overlapping they are
greatly overlapping but there's some
divergence and so what that results in
is real tension over things that matter
and anybody who goes into marriage
thinking that it's going to be like a
fairy tale has another thing coming to
them that I think results in us making
an error which is people because they
have the wrong idea about what a
functional marriage is supposed to look
like if they run into those tensions
they often imagine that that is either
the result of them failing to do it well
or the result of the fact that the
entire idea of marriage is bogus to
begin with well in fact our terminology
surrounding how one finds themself
married under
modern circumstances where you're not
set up in a marriage by your parents or
something the terminology is very
confusing to begin with because when
somebody is smitten in the extreme we
say that they've fallen in love and the
state that they are in that deep
infatuation is in many ways a profoundly
dishonest state and one that may give
way to real love or it may not but that
state appears designed to cause a person
to act in an unsustainable way that is
better than their normal self you know
effectively it allows a person to
mislead another person into believing
better of them than would be fair and
when two people fall in love with each
other they're both sort of actively
lying about who they really are it's not
intentional it's not conscious but the
infatuated state is temporary
unsustainable and not accurate with
respect to how a person is actually
going to be in the long-term when that
state wears off one finds out if the
relationship that remains behind is
actually one of true love and the nature
of that true love relationship is
actually truly giving it doesn't really
work America's not going to function it
can last but it won't function well if
people do not view each other as
similarly important to self in other
words there's something inherently
selfless about a state of true love and
that is not the nature of infatuation
and saturation is almost the opposite
state I don't want to represent love as
completely selfless a person does not
surrender their entire self in
of a loving relationship but what they
effectively do is they put their partner
on a level playing field that is to say
they will genuinely sacrifice for the
well-being of their partner and the
partner will do the same and that is
what I would call true love which I
wouldn't I wouldn't say is in contrast
to romantic love I think that is
romantic love what it isn't is
infatuation infatuation is the very
early unsustainable state and the what
I'm calling true love is almost by
definition a sustainable state it's
something that can last and grow and can
govern the way a relationship functions
but a way to think of it does involve
basically instead of thinking of
selflessness it is at least equally good
to say that it is a broadening of the
concept of self to include another and
then to include offspring and that's
what it feels like to well at a
traditional circumcise a legal construct
that we call marriage and then there's a
pair bond that is meant to be indefinite
and they don't necessarily overlap there
are lots of places where people may not
have the money to get legally married
but they sign up for the Uniform all
contract nonetheless what would have
been true until birth control is that a
reproductive behavior would have in most
circumstance waited until that contract
was nailed down until people had agreed
to be together and the reason for that
is that females have everything to lose
if they sign up for such an agreement
informally they go to bed and get
fertilized and then the guy runs off
that's such a great deal for a male
evolutionarily speaking in such a
terrible deal for a woman evolutionarily
speaking that essentially all of our
courtship rituals are built around
unearthing that false desire to to
procreate so falling in love would have
been accompanied by
intense desire and it might have
resulted in a decision to marry in order
to be able to have sex but agreeing to
have sex because you're in a promising
relationship that might result in
marriage doesn't make any sense because
actually the incentives for males work
exactly the other way at the point that
a woman has become pregnant without
nailing down the requirement of
commitment the guy might actually be
favored to leave because he that's
that's a freebie and he can go start
another family and invest the resources
that would have gone to that woman in
her offspring in somebody else we tend
to have the sense that marriage requires
something special in order for it to
evolve and in fact that's the opposite
of the case in birds something like 85%
are monogamous in some form that we
recognize are there within a season or
across a lifetime in mammals it's less
than 15% why the difference well it
comes down to something physiological
which interrupts the value of monogamy
within mammals teaming up to raise
offspring that require a lot of
investment is very valuable and
increases the chances of those offspring
being successful what gets in the way is
that in mammals males have a high
likelihood of being uncertain of their
paternity that because of the way
mammals reproduce because of internal
just safe males don't necessarily know
when a female that they have made it
with gives birth whether the offspring
that she just gave birth to is theirs or
not and so selection favors them not to
invest in offspring that they are
uncertain of the paternity of and so it
is harder for monogamy to evolve in
birds the eggs are fertilized right
before they're laid so the amount of
time that a male has to be able to
account for a female's whereabouts is
much shorter in order for him to know
that the offspring is his and so
monogamy
readily evolved so what this means is
that there's an advantage to these
intensive pair bonds the advantage is it
allows the raising of children that are
better cared for which then allows for
the the evolution of what we call ultra
she ality helplessness in the young
helplessness is not in and of itself a
good thing but the ability to be
helpless and be cared for by two parents
allows the evolution of high degrees of
behavioral complexity and so it has
advantages and what what this really
suggests is that yes pair bonding is
valuable in many circumstances and the
universe keeps telling us that by
producing it in different taxa that
aren't related to each other and
marriage is this elaboration of these
pair bonds in the context of a creature
that picks up most of what it is
behaviorally as a software update after
it's born and so the idea of parents who
have this repository of humaneness that
they carry around in their minds rather
than their genomes and then they pass on
to offspring in a way that can be
augmented and modified for changes in
circumstance or new discoveries that is
an amazingly powerful phenomenon and it
is not in any way incidental human
beings are all about the software
monogamous pair bonds that raise
offspring are all about transmitting
that software to the next generation and
to parents raising children together is
the ideal way for that to work so there
are many asymmetries between men and
women if we if we look at what they
would have been like in ancestral
circumstances and I'm an advocate for
the idea that all of these things can be
opened up and we can decide some of
these asymmetries may not be desirable
we shouldn't want to perpetuate them
into the future some of them may be
desirable but we want to democratize the
content so we may want to take stuff
that's traditionally
masculine and and make it available to
everybody and likewise some of the stuff
that's feminine we may want to make it
available to everybody in general I
would say that there is a dichotomy
between males and females under
ancestral circumstances that comes from
the fact that females are much lower
variance than males with respect to how
many offspring they can produce females
are limited by the rate at which they
can get pregnant nurse a child to wean
it and then get pregnant again and so
that puts a relatively low limit on the
number of offspring that can be produced
in a lifetime a man if he is having sex
without commitment can produce an
indefinitely large number of offspring
in a lifetime so that high variance
versus low variance distinction has all
kinds of implications for the way men
and women have traditionally viewed the
world and I think it results in
essentially two different toolkits of
wisdom that have traveled through
humanity's past one of them has
travelled a female path that would be a
kind of farsighted wisdom that comes
closer to matching the well-being of the
population at large because a female
can't get lucky and produce a hundred
offspring in a lifetime her Oscar
Fitness is largely a matter of how well
her population persists through time and
therefore how good a home it provides
for whatever offspring she produces
males because they're high variance are
much more likely to have wisdom about
high-risk high-reward activities and if
we think about some of the things that
men are traditionally imagined to be
involved in stuff like getting on a ship
and going over the horizon to see what's
over there that's a it's a very
dangerous behavior and most of the men
who did that probably didn't come back
but those who did came back sometimes
came back big winners and so that a
high-risk high-reward kind of wisdom is
likely to have tried
the mail path there's no reason though
that these kinds of wisdom can't be made
general that a woman who wants to get
involved in high-risk high-reward
activities should have access to that
wisdom too but we shouldn't necessarily
imagine that everybody will just pick it
up automatically the nature of wisdom is
that actually it takes experience and
exposure in order to discover it and so
whatever it is that teaches men how to
think in this way is something that
probably needs to be available to
everybody doesn't mean women will be
inherently as interested in it they may
be they may not be but they should have
access to it and likewise males should
certainly have access to the toolkit of
female wisdom however it is that that's
accumulated amongst women probably we
would be in a lot better circumstance
environmentally if men who have had an
awful lot of say over how the world is
governed had a long term view about
well-being rather than a very narrow
competitive short term to you the story
the mythology surrounding oppression of
females by a patriarchal force that
mythology causes a tragic miscalculation
men have to reproductive strategies one
reproductive strategy I will call sew
and go that is love them and leave them
that love them and leave was strategy
would have been very rarely successful
in the ancestral past because females
are so thoroughly built and schooled to
avoid allowing it to happen the cost of
raising an offspring
alone is so high that females have done
everything in their power to prevent
this from occurring nonetheless males
are focused on it because when it
happens it's such an evolutionary
bargain that it's a huge win it's like
it's like a winning lottery ticket
so the commonality of it would have been
low but the value of it when it happened
to an individual male that have been
high that causes males to always be on
the lookout for this possibility on the
other hand the way males would have
typically reproduced inside of a society
would have been to invest in a female
to pair-bond with them and to invest in
their offspring and that's a lower
variance strategy but it is nonetheless
the more common way of getting there
in that phase looking for a mate in whom
to invest for the long haul males
females are much more similar a male
who's looking for a wife is much more
like a female looking for a husband than
a male looking to score and so what this
means is that males have these two
phases and one of them is Randy and not
very interesting and somehow this
mythology surrounding the oppressive
patriarchy has led people to imagine
that in order for women to be equal to
men they have to quote/unquote behave
like men and to behave like men doesn't
mean like behaving like men in their
best phase
it means behaving like men in their most
frivolous stupid and least reliable
phase so what we're effectively doing is
instead of having the virtues of
masculinity be democratized so women
have those things available to them what
we have is stupid male behavior being
delivered to females as if it were the
height of sophistication and it's
resulting in a dysfunctional society in
which nothing seems to work and you know
we're talking about new rules for
sexuality and which one constantly needs
to seek you know the re-establishment of
consent or whatever it is and it's just
not very healthy there is a way in which
males in a culture with healthy
masculinity mature into an ability to do
extraordinary things to stay cool under
fire all sorts of things like that and
those are highly desirable
characteristics by synonymous in
maleness with
yeah aggro getting lucky stuff we
destroy the high quality version of
masculinity and we put in its place a
low-quality version of masculinity and
frankly the female analogue this
masculinity that is Unleashed superhero
female that you're talking about is a
fiction alright it doesn't really work
and I would say the women who I know who
have these may be traditionally
masculine characteristics who really
pull it off who are really super capable
and you know who you would want to to
have on your team under under terrible
circumstances it looks much more like a
traditional masculinity than it does
like some modern made-up version so you
said there's the to evolutionary
strategies there's so ago yeah that's a
terrible way to put it but yes yeah I
mean you know the thing is this exists
in the mythology - right men sow their
Wild Oats and then they settle down now
settling down makes it sound awful but
really what they do is they they wise up
you know I had a mentor when I was in
graduate school very interesting guy
very one-off kind of guy who had certain
kinds of wisdom and he used to talk
about the difference in men after their
libido stop jerking him around and his
basic point was it's very hard to
concentrate when your libido you know is
pointing you this way in that way and
that when that lets you go suddenly you
have access to your full mental
faculties to point at problems that are
actually worthy of your attention you
still have a dry
masculine force but now you get to
concentrate it on the building or a
larger project or family or something
like that
totally yeah yeah I get to actually get
to be a man I guess there's a lot of
discussion in society about whether or
not monogamy is a problem to be solved
in other words if it is some kind of
puritanical instinct that is holding us
back from what we really are
biologically this is nonsense
monogamy is an evolved state and it has
served the populations that most of us
come from very well do we need to
maintain it I can't say for sure I can
say that the alternative that people are
advancing polyamory is not likely to be
stable and it is almost certainly going
to devolve into polygyny that in a state
where people are lowering the bar to
mating what ultimately happens is those
people who are powerful those men who
are powerful end up accumulating many
mates and many men get frozen out by the
fact that their lower status when that
happens you produce a situation that is
not healthy for society whether
individuals choose to do this or not
civilization has a lot to lose if it's
creating sexually frustrated males those
males ultimately become armies somebody
decides to arm them and point them at
some population that can't defend
themselves or they become violent so
there's a lot to be said from society's
perspective for monogamy being the state
that is the best that is the most
compatible with the values that we all
share there's also a lot to be said for
the fact that from an individual point
of view it is also the most rewarding
state that people fantasize just as
people sometimes a vote as if they were
very very wealthy when they're not
they imagine that like they might become
wealthy when we talk about what sorts of
mating systems make sense people
probably imagine that they're going to
be on the winning end of it and to the
extent that women are evolutionarily set
up to evaluate different mating
opportunities in particular ways they
are liable to find what actually evolves
in a polyamorous situation disappointing
and men are liable to find out that
unless they're at the top of the
hierarchy
it isn't very satisfying either so if
our real point is individual human
satisfaction in the context of sex love
and romance
monogamy is the way to go in addition to
the benefits that provides of just being
safer for civilization what I think
probably would be surprising to people
is that because monogamy has a
relatively long history in human beings
that the difficulty of behaving in a
monogamous way is not zero but it is
less than people imagine when people
sign up for a monogamous relationship
there's a certain terror about it that
comes from the way comics talk about it
and come comes from the sorts of things
you know set around the campfire but the
fact is because monogamy has been highly
successful at allowing people to produce
offspring and raise them to team up
there is effectively a program for
behaving monogamously inside of human
beings yes even human males and that the
discovery that it is not the struggle
that you think it's going to be because
in fact if you look for at the wiring is
there is would probably be a relief to a
lot of people who spend a tremendous
amount of effort imagining that they're
going to get trapped in something that's
torture
you